Man or beast.
Nightmare Alley is a crime, drama, thriller film directed by Guillermo del Toro.
An ambitious carnival man with a talent for manipulating people with a few well-chosen words
hooks up with a female psychologist who is even more dangerous than he is.
Stanton Carlisle, played by Bradley Cooper.
Dr. Lilith Ritter, played by Cate Blanchett.
Zeena the Seer, played by Toni Collette.
Clem Hoatley, played by Willem Dafoe.
Ezra Grindle, played by Richard Jenkins.
Molly Cahill, played by Rooney Mara.
Nightmare Alley is a 2021 neo-noir psychological thriller film co-written and directed by Guillermo
del Toro, and based on the 1946 novel of the same name by William Lindsay Gresham.
It is the second feature film adaptation of
Gresham's novel, following the 1947 film.
A co-production between Searchlight Pictures and Double Dare You Productions, the film stars Bradley Cooper as a
charming and ambitious carnival worker with a mysterious past who takes big risks to boost his career.
Cate Blanchett, Toni Collette, Willem Dafoe, Richard Jenkins, Rooney Mara,
Ron Perlman, Mary Steenburgen, and David Strathairn also star.
Del Toro announced the film in 2017, and he produced the film alongside J.
Miles Dale and Cooper.
Frequent collaborator Dan Laustsen was the cinematographer, and Nathan
Johnson replaced Alexandre Desplat as its composer.
Principal photography began in January 2020 in Toronto, Ontario, but was
shut down in March 2020 due to the COVID-19 pandemic.
Production resumed in September 2020 and concluded that December.
Nightmare Alley premiered at Alice Tully Hall in New York City on December 1, 2021, and was
theatrically released in the United States on December 17, 2021, by Searchlight Pictures.
It received generally positive reviews from critics, who praised Del Toro’s direction, the cinematography, score,
production design, and performances of Cooper and Blanchett, while criticizing the film's runtime.
The film flopped at the box office, grossing a total of $39.6 million
worldwide against a $60 million production budget.
It received four nominations at the 94th Academy Awards, including Best Picture.
A black-and-white version subtitled Vision in Darkness and Light was
released in select cities starting on January 14, 2022.
The film explores themes of infidelity, based on novel or
book, love triangle, tarot cards, mentor.
The tone is intense and dark and emotional.